{"author": "Robert R. Harr","data": [{"chapter": "4.1","questions": [{"data": [{"choices": ["Genotyping","Phenotyping","Both genotyping and phenotyping","Polymerase chain reaction"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Phenotyping","explanation": "Phenotyping, or the physical expression of a genotype, is the type of testing routinely performed in the blood bank. An individual, for example, may have the AO genotype but phenotypes as group A"},"question": "What type of serological testing does the blood bank technologist perform when determining the blood group of a patient?","reference": "Blood bank/Apply knowledge of laboratory operations/Genetics/1"},{"choices": ["Dosage","Linkage disequilibrium","Homozygosity","Heterozygosity"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Dosage","explanation": "Dosage is defined as an antibody reacting stronger with homozygous cells (e.g., KK) than with heterozygous cells (e.g., Kk). In addition to Kell, dosage effect is seen commonly with antigens M, N, S, s, Fya, Fyb, Jka, Jkb, and the antigens of the Rh system"},"question": "If anti-K reacts 3+ with a donor cell with a genotype KK and 2+ with a Kk cell, the antibody is demonstrating:","reference": "Blood bank/Apply knowledge of fundamental biological characteristics/Genetics/Kell/3"},{"choices": ["Gender", "Race", "Gender and race", "Medication"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Gender and race","explanation": "The frequency of Duffy antigens Fya and Fyb varies with race. The Fy(a-b-) phenotype occurs in almost 70% of African Americans and is very rare in whites. Xga antigen is X-linked and, therefore, expressed more frequently in women (who may inherit the antigen from either parent) than in men"},"question": "Carla expresses the blood group antigens Fya, Fyb, and Xga. James shows expressions of none of these antigens. What factor(s) may account for the absence of these antigens in James?","reference": "Blood bank/Apply knowledge of fundamental biological characteristics/Genetics/2"},{"choices": ["An individual with the BO genotype is homozygous for B antigen","An individual with the BB genotype is homozygous for B antigen","An individual with the OO genotype is heterozygous for O antigen","An individual with the AB phenotype is homozygous for A and B antigens"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "An individual with the BB genotype is homozygous for B antigen","explanation": "An individual having the BB genotype has inherited the B gene from both parents and, therefore, is homozygous for B antigen"},"question": "Which of the following statements is true?","reference": "Blood bank/Apply knowledge of fundamental biological characteristics/Genetics/ABO/1"},{"choices": ["DCe/dce", "DCE/DCE", "Dce/dce", "DCE/dCe"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "DCe/dce","explanation": "The genotype DCe/dce contains one C and one c gene and is heterozygous for C and c antigens"},"question": "Which genotype is heterozygous for C?","reference": "Blood bank/Apply knowledge of fundamental biological characteristics/Genetics/Rh/2"},{"choices": ["HH only", "HH and Hh", "Hh and hh", "hh only"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "hh only","explanation": "The Bombay phenotype will be expressed only when no H substance is present. The Oh type is expressed by the genotype hh. Bombay phenotypes produce naturally occurring anti-H, and their serum agglutinates group O red blood cells (RBCs) in addition to RBCs from persons who are groups A, B, and AB"},"question": "Which genotype(s) will give rise to the Bombay phenotype?","reference": "Blood bank/Apply knowledge of fundamental biological characteristics/ABO/Bombay/1"},{"choices": ["1N", "2N", "3N", "4N"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "1N","explanation": "Meiosis involves two nuclear divisions in succession resulting in four gametocytes, each containing half the number of chromosomes found in somatic cells or 1N"},"question": "Meiosis in cell division is limited to the ova and sperm producing four gametes containing what complement of DNA?","reference": "Blood bank/Apply knowledge of fundamental biological characteristics/Genetics/1"},{"choices": ["Interphase", "Prophase", "Anaphase", "Telophase"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Interphase","explanation": "Interphase is the stage in between cell divisions. The cell is engaged in metabolic activity. Chromosomes are not clearly discerned; however, nucleoli may be visible"},"question": "A cell that is not actively dividing is said to be in:","reference": "Blood bank/Apply knowledge of fundamental biological characteristics/Genetics/1"},{"choices": ["Dominant", "Recessive", "Codominant", "Corecessive"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Codominant","explanation": "The inheritance of most blood group genes is codominant, meaning that no gene or allele is dominant over another. For example, a person who is group AB expresses both the A and B antigen on his or her RBCs"},"question": "Which of the following describes the expression of most blood group antigens?","reference": "Blood bank/Apply knowledge of fundamental biological characteristics/Genetics/1"},{"choices": ["AB", "A or B", "O", "All are possible"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "All are possible","explanation": "A mating between AO and BO persons can result in an offspring with blood type A, B, AB, or O"},"question": "What blood type is not possible for an offspring of an AO and BO mating?","reference": "Blood bank/Apply knowledge of fundamental biological characteristics/Genetics/ABO/2"},{"choices": ["Direct/primary/first order","Probability","Random","Indirect/secondary/second order"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Indirect/secondary/second order","explanation": "An indirect/secondary/second order, exclusion occurs when a genetic marker is absent in the child but should have been transmitted by the alleged father. In this case, either A or B should be present in the child"},"question": "The alleged father of a child in a disputed case of paternity is blood group AB. The mother is group O, and the child is group O. What type of exclusion is this?","reference": "Blood bank/Evaluate laboratory data to verify test results/Genotype/Paternity testing/2"},{"choices": ["Crossing over","Linkage disequilibrium","Polymorphism","Chimerism"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Linkage disequilibrium","explanation": "Linkage disequilibrium is a phenomenon in which alleles situated in close proximity on a chromosome associate with one another more than would be expected from individual allelic frequencies"},"question": "If the frequency of gene Y is 0.4 and the frequency of gene Z is 0.5, one would expect that they should occur together 0.2 (20%) of the time. In actuality, they are found together 32% of the time. This is an example of:","reference": "Blood bank/Apply principles of genetics/3 Answers to Questions 6–12"},{"choices": ["The heterozygous population of one allele","The homozygous population of one allele","The recessive allele","The dominant allele"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "The homozygous population of one allele","explanation": "In the Hardy-Weinberg formula (p2 + 2pq + q2), p2 and q2 represent homozygous expressions, and 2pq represents heterozygous expression. This formula is used in population genetics to determine the frequency of different alleles"},"question": "In the Hardy-Weinberg formula, p2 represents:","reference": "Blood bank/Apply knowledge of fundamental biological characteristics/Genetics/1"},{"choices": ["Autosomal dominant","Autosomal recessive","X-linked dominant","X-linked recessive"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "X-linked dominant","explanation": "In X-linked dominant inheritance, there is absence of male-to-male transmission because a male passes his Y chromosome to all of his sons and his single X chromosome to all his daughters. All daughters who inherit the affected gene will express the trait. An example of this type of inheritance is the Xga blood group"},"question": "In this type of inheritance, the father carries the trait on his X chromosome. He has no sons with the trait because he passed his Y chromosome to his sons; however, all his daughters will express the trait.","reference": "Blood bank/Apply knowledge of fundamental biological characteristics/Genetics/1"},{"choices": ["IgM antibodies are larger molecules and have the ability to bind more antigen","IgM antibodies tend to clump together more readily to bind more antigen","IgM antibodies are found in greater concentrations than IgG antibodies","IgM antibodies are not limited by subclass specificity"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "IgM antibodies are larger molecules and have the ability to bind more antigen","explanation": "An IgM molecule has the potential to bind up to 10 antigens compared with a molecule of IgG, which can bind only two"},"question": "Why do immunoglobulin M (IgM) antibodies, such as those formed against ABO antigens, have the ability to directly agglutinate RBCs and cause visible agglutination?","reference": "Blood bank/Apply knowledge of fundamental biological characteristics/Antibodies/1"},{"choices": ["Low ionic strength solution (LISS)","Polyethylene glycol","Polybrene","Dithiothreitol-papain (ZZAP)"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Low ionic strength solution (LISS)","explanation": "LISS contains a reduced concentration of NaCl (0.2%) and results in a reduction in charged ions within the ionic cloud, decreasing the zeta potential and facilitating antigen–antibody interaction"},"question": "Which of the following enhancement mediums decreases the zeta potential, allowing antibody and antigen to come closer together?","reference": "Blood bank/Apply knowledge of fundamental biological characteristics/Antigens/1"},{"choices": ["Primary", "Secondary", "Tertiary", "Anaphylactic"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Secondary","explanation": "An anamnestic response is a secondary immune response in which memory lymphocytes respond rapidly to foreign antigen in producing specific antibody. The antibodies are IgG and are produced at lower doses of antigen than in the primary response"},"question": "This type of antibody response is analogous to an anamnestic antibody reaction.","reference": "Blood bank/Apply knowledge of fundamental biological characteristics/Antibodies/1"},{"choices": ["Anti-IgG and anti-C3a","Anti-IgG and anti-C3d","Anti-IgG and anti-IgM","All of these options"],"correctAnswer": {"answer": "Anti-IgG and anti-C3d","explanation": "In the direct antiglobulin test (DAT), rabbit polyspecific antisera contains both an anti-human IgG component and an antibody against the C3d component of complement"},"question": "Which antibodies to a component of complement are contained in the rabbit polyspecific anti-human globulin (AHG) reagent for detection of in vivo sensitization?","reference": "Blood bank/Apply knowledge of fundamental biological characteristics/AHG/2"}],"type": "MULTIPLE_CHOICE"}],"topic": "Genetics and Immunology of Blood Groups"}],"edition": "5th","title": "Medical Laboratory Science Review"}